<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
    <link type="text/css" rel="stylesheet" id="dark-mode-custom-link"/>
    <link type="text/css" rel="stylesheet" id="dark-mode-general-link"/>
    <style lang="en" type="text/css" id="dark-mode-custom-style"/>
    <style lang="en" type="text/css" id="dark-mode-native-style"/>
    <style lang="en" type="text/css" id="dark-mode-native-sheet"/>
    <text lang="en">
        <body>
            <div1 type="sura" n="17" org="uniform" sample="complete" author="Pickthall">
                <p>
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/> Glorified be He Who carried His servant by night
                    from the Inviolable Place of Worship to the Far distant place of worship the
                    neighbourhood whereof We have blessed, that We might show him of Our tokens! Lo!
                    He, only He, is the Hearer, the Seer. <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/> We gave
                    unto Moses the Scripture, and We appointed it a guidance for the children of
                    Israel, saying: Choose no guardian beside Me. <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                    (They were) the seed of those whom We carried (in the ship) along with Noah. Lo!
                    he was a grateful slave. <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/> And We decreed for the
                    Children of Israel in the Scripture: Ye verily will work corruption in the earth
                    twice, and ye will become great tyrants. <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/> So when
                    the time for the first of the two came, We roused against you slaves of Ours of
                    great might who ravaged (your) country, and it was a threat performed.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/> Then we gave you once again your turn
                    against them, and We aided you with wealth and children and made you more in
                    soldiery. <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/> (Saying): If ye do good, ye do good
                    for your own souls, and if ye do evil, it is for them (in like manner). So, when
                    the time for the second (of the judgments) came (We roused against you others of
                    Our slaves) to ravage you, and to enter the Temple <comparison>even as they entered it the
                    first time</comparison>, and to lay waste all that they conquered with an utter wasting.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/> It may be that your Lord will have mercy on
                    you, but <repetition>if ye repeat (the crime) We shall repeat (the punishment)</repetition>, and We have
                    appointed hell a dungeon for the disbelievers. <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                    Lo! this Qur'an guideth unto that which is straightest, and giveth tidings unto
                    the believers who do good works that theirs will be a great reward. <milestone
                        unit="verse" n="10"/> And that those who believe not in the Hereafter, for
                    them We have prepared a painful doom. <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/> Man
                    prayeth for evil as he prayeth for good; for man was ever hasty. <milestone
                        unit="verse" n="12"/> And We appoint the night and the day two portents.
                    Then We make dark the portent of the night, and We make the portent of the day
                    sight-giving, that ye may seek bounty from your Lord, and that ye may know the
                    computation of the years, and the reckoning; and everything have <repetition>We expounded
                    with a clear expounding.</repetition> <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/> And every man's augury
                    have We fastened to his own neck, and We shall bring forth for him on the Day of
                    Resurrection a book which he will find wide open. <milestone unit="verse" n="14"
                    /> (And it will be said unto him): Read thy Book. Thy soul sufficeth as reckoner
                    against thee this day. <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/> <repetition>Whosoever goeth right,
                    it is only for (the good of) his own soul that he goeth right</repetition>, and <repetition>whosoever
                    erreth, erreth only</repetition> to its hurt. No laden soul can bear another's load, We never
                    punish until we have sent a messenger. <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/> And when
                    We would destroy a township We send commandment to its folk who live at ease,
                    and afterward they commit abomination therein, and so the Word (of doom) hath
                    effect for it, and <repetition>we annihilate it with complete annihilation.</repetition> <milestone
                        unit="verse" n="17"/> How many generations have We destroyed since Noah! And
                    Allah sufficeth as Knower and Beholder of the sins of His slaves. <milestone
                        unit="verse" n="18"/> Whoso desireth that (life) which hasteneth away, We
                    hasten for him therein what We will for whom We please. And afterward We have
                    appointed for him hell; he will endure the heat thereof, condemned, rejected.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/> And whoso desireth the Hereafter and
                    striveth for it with the effort necessary, being a believer; for such, their
                    effort findeth favour (with their Lord). <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/> Each
                    do We supply, both these and those, from the bounty of thy Lord. And the bounty
                    of thy Lord can never be walled up. <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/> See how We
                    prefer one of them above another, and verily the Hereafter will be greater in
                    degrees and greater in preferment. <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/> Set not up
                    with Allah any other god (O man) lest thou sit down reproved, forsaken.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="23"/> Thy Lord hath decreed, that ye worship none
                    save Him, and (that ye show) kindness to parents. If one of them or both of them
                    attain old age with thee, say not "Fie" unto them nor repulse them, but speak
                    unto them a gracious word. <milestone unit="verse" n="24"/> And lower unto them
                    the wing of submission through mercy, and say: My Lord! Have mercy on them both
                    as they did care for me when I was little. <milestone unit="verse" n="25"/> Your
                    Lord is Best Aware of what is in your minds. If ye are righteous, then lo! He
                    was ever Forgiving unto those who turn (unto Him). <milestone unit="verse"
                        n="26"/> Give the kinsman his due, and the needy, and the wayfarer, and
                    squander not (thy wealth) in wantonness. <milestone unit="verse" n="27"/> Lo!
                    the squanderers were ever brothers of the devils, and the devil was ever an
                    ingrate to his Lord. <milestone unit="verse" n="28"/> But if thou turn away from
                    them, seeking mercy from thy Lord, for which thou hopest, then speak unto them a
                    reasonable word. <milestone unit="verse" n="29"/> And let not thy hand be
                    chained to thy neck nor open it with a complete opening, lest thou sit down
                    rebuked, denuded. <milestone unit="verse" n="30"/> Lo! thy Lord enlargeth the
                    provision for whom He will, and straiteneth (it for whom He will). Lo, He was
                    ever Knower, Seer of His slaves. <milestone unit="verse" n="31"/> Slay not your
                    children, fearing a fall to poverty, We shall provide for them and for you. Lo!
                    the slaying of them is great sin. <milestone unit="verse" n="32"/> And come not
                    near unto adultery. Lo! it is an abomination and an evil way. <milestone
                        unit="verse" n="33"/> And slay not the life which Allah hath forbidden save
                    with right. Whoso is slain wrongfully, We have given power unto his heir, but
                    let him not commit excess in slaying. Lo! he will be helped. <milestone
                        unit="verse" n="34"/> Come not near the wealth of the orphan save with that
                    which is better till he come to strength; and keep the covenant. Lo! of the
                    covenant it will be asked. <milestone unit="verse" n="35"/> Fill the measure
                    when ye measure, and weigh with a right balance; that is meet, and better in the
                    end. <milestone unit="verse" n="36"/> (O man), follow not that whereof thou hast
                    no knowledge. Lo! the hearing and the sight and the heart - of each of these it
                    will be asked. <milestone unit="verse" n="37"/> And walk not in the earth
                    exultant. Lo! thou canst not rend the earth, nor canst thou stretch to the
                    height of the hills. <milestone unit="verse" n="38"/> The evil of all that is
                    hateful in the sight of thy Lord. <milestone unit="verse" n="39"/> This is
                    (part) of that wisdom wherewith thy Lord hath inspired thee (O Muhammad). And
                    set not up with Allah any other god, lest thou be cast into hell, reproved,
                    abandoned. <milestone unit="verse" n="40"/> Hath your Lord then distinguished
                    you (O men of Makka) by giving you sons, and hath chosen for Himself females
                    from among the angels? Lo! verily ye speak an awful word! <milestone
                        unit="verse" n="41"/> We verily have displayed (Our warnings) in this Qur'an
                    that they may take heed, but it increaseth them in naught save aversion.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="42"/> Say (O Muhammad, to the disbelievers): If
                    there were other gods along with Him, as they say, then had they sought a way
                    against the Lord of the Throne. <milestone unit="verse" n="43"/> Glorified is
                    He, and High Exalted above what they say! <milestone unit="verse" n="44"/> The
                    seven heavens and the earth and all that is therein praise Him, and there is not
                    a thing but hymneth His praise; but ye understand not their praise. Lo! He is
                    ever Clement, Forgiving. <milestone unit="verse" n="45"/> And when thou recitest
                    the Qur'an we place between thee and those who believe not in the Hereafter a
                    hidden barrier; <milestone unit="verse" n="46"/> And We place upon their hearts
                    veils lest they should understand it, and in their ears a deafness; and when
                    thou makest mention of thy Lord alone in the Qur'an, they turn their backs in
                    aversion. <milestone unit="verse" n="47"/> We are Best Aware of what they wish
                    to hear when they give ear to thee and when they take secret counsel, when the
                    evil-doers say: Ye follow but a man bewitched. <milestone unit="verse" n="48"/>
                    See what similitudes they coin for thee, and thus are all astray, and cannot
                    find a road! <milestone unit="verse" n="49"/> And they say: When we are bones
                    and fragments, shall we forsooth, be raised up as a new creation? <milestone
                        unit="verse" n="50"/> Say: Be ye stones or iron <milestone unit="verse"
                        n="51"/> Or some created thing that is yet greater in your thoughts! Then
                    they will say: Who shall bring us back (to life). Say: He Who created you at the
                    first. Then will they shake their heads at thee, and say: When will it be? Say:
                    It will perhaps be soon; <milestone unit="verse" n="52"/> A day when He will
                    call you and ye will answer with His praise, and ye will think that ye have
                    tarried but a little while. <milestone unit="verse" n="53"/> Tell My bondmen to
                    speak that which is kindlier. Lo! the devil soweth discord among them. Lo! the
                    devil is for man an open foe. <milestone unit="verse" n="54"/> Your Lord is Best
                    Aware of you. If He will, He will have mercy on you, or if He will, He will
                    punish you. We have not sent thee (O Muhammad) as a warden over them. <milestone
                        unit="verse" n="55"/> And thy Lord is Best Aware of all who are in the
                    heavens and the earth. And we preferred some of the prophets above others, and
                    unto David We gave the Psalms. <milestone unit="verse" n="56"/> Say: Cry unto
                    those (saints and angels) whom ye assume (to be gods) beside Him, yet they have
                    no power to rid you of misfortune nor to change. <milestone unit="verse" n="57"
                    /> Those unto whom they cry seek the way of approach to their Lord, which of
                    them shall be the nearest; they hope for His mercy and they fear <repetition>His doom. Lo!
                    the doom of thy Lord</repetition> is to be shunned. <milestone unit="verse" n="58"/> There is
                    not a township but We shall destroy it ere the Day of Resurrection, or punish it
                    with dire punishment. That is set forth in the Book (of Our decrees). <milestone
                        unit="verse" n="59"/> Naught hindereth Us from sending portents save that
                    the folk of old denied them. And We gave Thamud the she-camel - a clear portent
                    save to warn. <milestone unit="verse" n="60"/> And (it was a warning) when we
                    told thee: Lo! thy Lord encompasseth mankind, and We appointed the sight which
                    We showed thee as an ordeal for mankind, and (likewise) the Accursed Tree in the
                    Qur'an. We warn them, but it increaseth them in naught save gross impiety.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="61"/> And when We said unto the angels: Fall down
                    prostrate before Adam and they fell prostrate all save Iblis, he said: Shall I
                    fall prostrate before that which Thou hast created of clay? <milestone
                        unit="verse" n="62"/> He said: Seest Thou this (creature) whom Thou hast
                    honoured above me, if Thou give me grace until the Day of Resurrection I verily
                    will seize his seed, save but a few. <milestone unit="verse" n="63"/> He said:
                    Go, and whosoever of them followeth thee - lo! hell will be your payment, ample
                    payment. <milestone unit="verse" n="64"/> And excite any of them whom thou canst
                    with thy voice, and urge thy horse and foot against them, and be a partner in
                    their wealth and children, and promise them. Satan promiseth them only to
                    deceive. <milestone unit="verse" n="65"/> Lo! My (faithful) bondmen - over them
                    thou hast no power, and thy Lord sufficeth as (their) guardian. <milestone
                        unit="verse" n="66"/> (O mankind), your Lord is He Who driveth for you the
                    ship upon the sea that ye may seek of His bounty. Lo! He was ever Merciful
                    toward you. <milestone unit="verse" n="67"/> And when harm toucheth you upon the
                    sea, all unto whom ye cry (for succour) fail save Him (alone), but when He
                    bringeth you safe to land, ye turn away, for man was ever thankless. <milestone
                        unit="verse" n="68"/> Feel ye then secure that He will not cause a slope of
                    the land to engulf you, or send a sand-storm upon you, and then ye will find
                    that ye have no protector? <milestone unit="verse" n="69"/> Or feel ye secure
                    that He will not return you to that (plight) a second time, and send against you
                    a hurricane of wind and drown you for your thanklessness, and then ye will not
                    find therein that ye have any avenger against Us? <milestone unit="verse" n="70"
                    /> Verily we have honoured the Children of Adam. We carry them on the land and
                    the sea, and have made provision of good things for them, and <repetition>have preferred
                    them above many of those whom We created with a marked preferment</repetition>. <milestone
                        unit="verse" n="71"/> On the day when We shall summon all men with their
                    record, whoso is given his book in his right hand - such will read their book
                    and they will not be wronged a shred. <milestone unit="verse" n="72"/> Whoso is
                    blind here will be blind in the Hereafter, and yet further from the road.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="73"/> And they indeed strove hard to beguile thee
                    (Muhammad) away from that wherewith We have inspired thee, that thou shouldst
                    invent other than it against Us; and then would they have accepted thee as a
                    friend. <milestone unit="verse" n="74"/> And if We had not made thee wholly firm
                    thou mightest almost have inclined unto them a little. <milestone unit="verse"
                        n="75"/> Then had we made thee taste a double (punishment) of living and a
                    double (punishment) of dying, then hadst thou found no helper against Us.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="76"/> And they indeed wished to scare thee from
                    the land that they might drive thee forth from thence, and then they would have
                    stayed (there) but a little after thee. <milestone unit="verse" n="77"/> (Such
                    was Our) method in the case of those whom We sent before thee (to mankind), and
                    thou wilt not find for Our method aught of power to change. <milestone
                        unit="verse" n="78"/> Establish worship at the going down of the sun until
                    the dark of night, and (the recital of) the Qur'an at dawn. Lo! (the recital of)
                    the Qur'an at dawn is ever witnessed. <milestone unit="verse" n="79"/> And some
                    part of the night awake for it, a largess for thee. It may be that thy Lord will
                    raise thee to a praised estate. <milestone unit="verse" n="80"/> And say: My
                    Lord! Cause me to come in with a firm incoming and to go out with a firm
                    outgoing. And give me from Thy presence a sustaining Power. <milestone
                        unit="verse" n="81"/> And say: Truth hath come and falsehood hath vanished
                    away. Lo! falsehood is ever bound to vanish. <milestone unit="verse" n="82"/>
                    And We reveal of the Qur'an that which is a healing and a mercy for believers
                    though it increase the evil-doers in naught save ruin. <milestone unit="verse"
                        n="83"/> And when We make life pleasant unto man, he turneth away and is
                    averse; and when ill toucheth him he is in despair. <milestone unit="verse"
                        n="84"/> Say: Each one doth according to his rule of conduct, and thy Lord
                    is Best Aware of him whose way is right. <milestone unit="verse" n="85"/> They
                    are asking thee concerning the Spirit. Say: The Spirit is by command of my Lord,
                    and of knowledge ye have been vouchsafed but little. <milestone unit="verse"
                        n="86"/> And if We willed We could withdraw that which We have revealed unto
                    thee, then wouldst thou find no guardian for thee against Us in respect thereof.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="87"/> (It is naught) save mercy from thy Lord.
                    Lo! His kindness unto thee was ever great. <milestone unit="verse" n="88"/> Say:
                    Verily, though mankind and the jinn should assemble to produce the like of this
                    Qur'an, they could not produce the like thereof though they were helpers one of
                    another. <milestone unit="verse" n="89"/> And verily We have displayed for
                    mankind in this Qur'an all kind of similitudes, but most of mankind refuse aught
                    save disbelief. <milestone unit="verse" n="90"/> And they say: We will not put
                    faith in thee till thou cause a spring to gush forth from the earth for us;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="91"/> Or thou have a garden of date-palms and
                    grapes, and cause rivers to gush forth therein abundantly; <milestone
                        unit="verse" n="92"/> Or thou cause the heaven to fall upon us piecemeal, as
                    thou hast pretended, or bring Allah and the angels as a warrant; <milestone
                        unit="verse" n="93"/> Or thou have a house of gold; or thou ascend up into
                    heaven, and even then we will put no faith in thine ascension till thou bring
                    down for us a book that we can read. Say (O Muhammad): My Lord be Glorified! Am
                    I aught save a mortal messenger? <milestone unit="verse" n="94"/> And naught
                    prevented mankind from believing when the guidance came unto them save that they
                    said: Hath Allah sent a mortal as (His) messenger? <milestone unit="verse"
                        n="95"/> Say: If there were in the earth angels walking secure, We had sent
                    down for them from heaven an angel as messenger. <milestone unit="verse" n="96"
                    /> Say: Allah sufficeth for a witness between me and you. Lo! He is Knower, Seer
                    of His slaves. <milestone unit="verse" n="97"/> And he whom Allah guideth, he is
                    led aright; while, as for him whom He sendeth astray, for them thou wilt find no
                    protecting friends beside Him, and We shall assemble them on the Day of
                    Resurrection on their faces, blind, dumb and deaf; their habitation will be
                    hell; whenever it abateth, We increase the flame for them. <milestone
                        unit="verse" n="98"/> That is their reward because they disbelieved Our
                    revelations and said: When we are bones and fragments shall we, forsooth, be
                    raised up as a new creation? <milestone unit="verse" n="99"/> Have they not seen
                    that Allah Who created the heavens and the earth is Able to create the like of
                    them, and hath appointed for them an end whereof there is no doubt? But the
                    wrong-doers refuse aught save disbelief. <milestone unit="verse" n="100"/> Say
                    (unto them): If ye possessed the treasures of the mercy of my Lord, ye would
                    surely hold them back for fear of spending, for man was ever grudging.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="101"/> And verily We gave unto Moses nine tokens,
                    clear proofs (of Allah's Sovereignty). Do but ask the Children of Israel how he
                    came unto them, then Pharaoh said unto him: Lo! I deem thee one bewitched, O
                    Moses. <milestone unit="verse" n="102"/> He said: In truth thou knowest that
                    none sent down these (portents) save the Lord of the heavens and the earth as
                    proofs, and lo! (for my part) I deem thee lost, O Pharaoh. <milestone
                        unit="verse" n="103"/> And he wished to scare them from the land, but We
                    drowned him and those with him, all together. <milestone unit="verse" n="104"/>
                    And We said unto the Children of Israel after him: Dwell in the land; but when
                    the promise of the Hereafter cometh to pass We shall bring you as a crowd
                    gathered out of various nations. <milestone unit="verse" n="105"/> With truth
                    have We sent it down, and with truth hath it descended. And We have sent thee as
                    naught else save a bearer of good tidings and a warner. <milestone unit="verse"
                        n="106"/> And (it is) a Qur'an that We have divided, that thou mayst recite
                    it unto mankind at intervals, and We have revealed it by (successive)
                    revelation. <milestone unit="verse" n="107"/> Say: Believe therein or believe
                    not, lo! those who were given knowledge before it, when it is read unto them,
                    fall down prostrate on their faces, adoring, <milestone unit="verse" n="108"/>
                    Saying: Glory to our Lord! Verily the promise of our Lord must be fulfilled.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="109"/> They fall down on their faces, weeping,
                    and it increaseth humility in them. <milestone unit="verse" n="110"/> Say (unto
                    mankind): Cry unto Allah, or cry unto the Beneficent, unto whichsoever ye cry
                    (it is the same). His are the most beautiful names. And thou (Muhammad), be not
                    loud-voiced in thy worship nor yet silent therein, but follow a way between.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="111"/> And say: Praise be to Allah, Who hath not
                    taken unto Himself a son, and Who hath no partner in the Sovereignty, nor hath
                    He any protecting friend through dependence. And <repetition>magnify Him with all
                    magnificence</repetition>. </p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
