<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI.2><text lang="en"><body><div1 type="sura" n="13" org="uniform" sample="complete"><p>
<milestone unit="verse" n="1" />A.L.M.R. These are the signs (or verses) of the Book: that which hath been revealed unto thee from thy Lord is the <repetition>Truth</repetition>; but most men believe not. 
<milestone unit="verse" n="2" /><personification><repetition>Allah</repetition> <parallelism>is He Who</parallelism> raised the heavens without any pillars that ye can see;</personification> is firmly established on the throne (of authority); <personification>He has subjected the sun and the moon (to his Law)!</personification> Each one runs (its course) for a term appointed. <personification>He doth regulate all affairs,</personification> explaining the signs in detail, that ye may believe with certainty in the meeting with your Lord. 
<milestone unit="verse" n="3" />And it <parallelism>is He who</parallelism> spread out the earth, and set thereon mountains standing firm and (flowing) rivers: and fruit of every kind He made in pairs, two and two: He draweth the night as a veil o'er the Day. Behold, verily in these things there are signs for those who consider! 
<milestone unit="verse" n="4" />And in the earth are tracts (diverse though) neighbouring, and gardens of vines and fields sown with corn, and palm trees - growing out of single roots or otherwise: watered with the same water, yet some of them We make more excellent than others to eat. Behold, verily in these things there are signs for those who understand! 
<milestone unit="verse" n="5" />If thou dost marvel (at their want of faith), strange is their saying: "When we are (actually) dust, shall we indeed then be in a creation renewed?" They are those who deny their Lord! They are those round whose necks will be yokes (of servitude): they will be Companions of the Fire, to dwell therein (for aye)! 
<milestone unit="verse" n="6" />They ask thee to hasten on the evil in preference to the good: Yet have come to pass, before them, (many) exemplary punishments! <personification><parallelism>But verily thy Lord is full of forgiveness for mankind for their wrong-doing, and verily thy Lord is (also) strict in punishment.</parallelism></personification> 
<milestone unit="verse" n="7" />And the Unbelievers say: "Why is not a sign sent down to him from his Lord?" But thou art truly a warner, and to every people a guide. 
<milestone unit="verse" n="8" /><personification><repetition>Allah</repetition> doth know</personification> what every female (womb) doth bear, by how much the wombs fall short (of their time or number) or do exceed. Every single thing is before His sight, in (due) proportion. 
<milestone unit="verse" n="9" />He knoweth the unseen and that which is open: <comparison type="metaphor">He is the Great, the Most High.</comparison> 
<milestone unit="verse" n="10" />It is the same (to Him) whether any of you conceal his speech or declare it openly; whether he lie hid by night or walk forth freely by day. 
<milestone unit="verse" n="11" />For each (such person) there are (angels) in succession, before and behind him: <personification>They guard him by command of <repetition>Allah</repetition>.</personification> <personification><repetition>Allah</repetition> does not change a people's lot unless they change what is in their hearts.</personification> But when (once)<personification> <repetition>Allah</repetition> willeth a people's punishment,</personification> there can be no turning it back, nor will they find, besides Him, any to protect. 
<milestone unit="verse" n="12" />It is He Who doth show you the lightning, by way both of fear and of hope: It is He Who doth raise up the clouds, heavy with (fertilising) rain! 
<milestone unit="verse" n="13" /><personification>Nay, thunder repeateth His praises, and so do the angels, with awe:</personification> He flingeth the loud-voiced thunder-bolts, and therewith He striketh whomsoever He will..yet these (are the men) who (dare to) dispute about <repetition>Allah</repetition>, with the strength of His power (supreme)! 
<milestone unit="verse" n="14" />For Him (alone) is prayer in <repetition>Truth</repetition>: any others that they call upon besides Him hear them no more than if they were to stretch forth their hands for water to reach their mouths but it reaches them not: for the prayer of those without Faith is nothing but (futile) wandering (in the mind). 
<milestone unit="verse" n="15" />Whatever beings there are in the heavens and the earth do prostrate themselves to <repetition>Allah</repetition> (Acknowledging subjection),- with good-will or in spite of themselves: so do their shadows in the morning and evenings. 
<milestone unit="verse" n="16" />Say: "Who is the Lord and Sustainer of the heavens and the earth?" Say: "(It is) <repetition>Allah</repetition>." Say: "Do ye then take (for worship) protectors other than Him, such as have no power either for good or for harm to themselves?" Say: "Are the blind equal with those who see? Or the depths of darkness equal with light?" Or do they assign to <repetition>Allah</repetition> partners who have created (anything) as He has created, so that the creation seemed to them similar? Say: "<repetition>Allah</repetition> is the Creator of all things: He is the One, the Supreme and Irresistible." 
<milestone unit="verse" n="17" />He sends down water from the skies, and the channels flow, each according to its measure: But the torrent bears away to foam that mounts up to the surface. Even so, from that (ore) which they heat in the fire, to make ornaments or utensils therewith, there is a scum likewise. Thus doth <parallelism><repetition>Allah</repetition> (by parables) show forth</parallelism> <repetition>Truth</repetition> and Vanity. <comparison type="simile">For the scum disappears like forth cast out;</comparison> while that which is for the good of mankind remains on the earth. Thus doth <parallelism><repetition>Allah</repetition> set forth parables.</parallelism> 
<milestone unit="verse" n="18" />For those who respond to their Lord, are (all) good things. But those who respond not to Him,- Even if they had all that is in the heavens and on earth, and as much more, (in vain) would they offer it for ransom. For them will the reckoning be terrible: their abode will be Hell,- what a bed of misery! 
 <milestone unit="verse" n="19" /><comparison type="simile">Is then one who doth know that that which hath been revealed unto thee from thy Lord is the <repetition>Truth</repetition>, like one who is blind?</comparison> It is those who are endued with understanding that receive admonition;- 
<milestone unit="verse" n="20" />Those who fulfil the covenant of <repetition>Allah</repetition> and fail not in their plighted word; 
<milestone unit="verse" n="21" />Those who join together those things which <personification><repetition>Allah</repetition> hath commanded</personification> to be joined, hold their Lord in awe, and fear the terrible reckoning; 
<milestone unit="verse" n="22" />Those who patiently persevere, seeking the countenance of their Lord; Establish regular prayers; spend, out of (the gifts) We have bestowed for their sustenance, secretly and openly; and turn off Evil with good: for such there is the final attainment of the (eternal) home,- 
<milestone unit="verse" n="23" />Gardens of perpetual bliss: they shall enter there, as well as the righteous among their fathers, their spouses, and their offspring: and angels shall enter unto them from every gate (with the salutation): 
<milestone unit="verse" n="24" />"Peace unto you for that ye persevered in patience! Now how excellent is the final home!" 
<milestone unit="verse" n="25" />But those who break the Covenant of <repetition>Allah</repetition>, after having plighted their word thereto, and cut asunder those things which <personification><repetition>Allah</repetition> has commanded</personification> to be joined, and work mischief in the land;- on them is the curse; for them is the terrible home! 
<milestone unit="verse" n="26" /><personification><repetition>Allah</repetition> doth enlarge, or grant by (strict) measure, the sustenance (which He giveth) to whomso He pleaseth.</personification> (The wordly) rejoice in the life of this world: But the life of this world is but little comfort in the Hereafter. 
<milestone unit="verse" n="27" />The Unbelievers say: "Why is not a sign sent down to him from his Lord?" Say: "Truly <repetition>Allah</repetition> leaveth, to stray, whom He will; But He guideth to Himself those who turn to Him in penitence,- 
<milestone unit="verse" n="28" />"Those who believe, and <personification>whose hearts find satisfaction </personification>in the remembrance of <repetition>Allah</repetition>: for without doubt in the remembrance of <repetition>Allah</repetition> do hearts find satisfaction. 
<milestone unit="verse" n="29" />"For those who believe and work righteousness, is (every) blessedness, and a beautiful place of (final) return." 
<milestone unit="verse" n="30" />Thus have we sent thee amongst a People before whom (long since) have (other) Peoples (gone and) passed away; in order that thou mightest rehearse unto them what We send down unto thee by inspiration; yet do they reject (Him), the Most Gracious! Say: "He is my Lord! There is no god but He! On Him is my trust, and to Him do I turn!" 
<milestone unit="verse" n="31" /><hyperbole>If there were a Qur'an with which mountains were moved, or the earth were cloven asunder, or the dead were made to speak,</hyperbole> (this would be the one!) But, truly, the command is with <repetition>Allah</repetition> in all things! Do not the Believers know, that, had <repetition>Allah</repetition> (so) willed, He could have guided all mankind (to the right)? But the Unbelievers,- never will disaster cease to seize them for their (ill) deeds, or to settle close to their homes, until the promise of <repetition>Allah</repetition> come to pass, for, <assertion>verily, <repetition>Allah</repetition> will not fail in His promise. 
<milestone unit="verse" n="32" />Mocked were (many) messengers before thee: but I granted respite to the unbelievers, and finally I punished them: Then how (terrible) was my requital! </assertion>
<milestone unit="verse" n="33" />Is then He who standeth over every soul (and knoweth) all that it doth, (like any others)? <irony>And yet they ascribe partners to <repetition>Allah</repetition>.</irony> Say: <rhetorical-question>"But name them! is it that ye will inform Him of something he knoweth not on earth, or is it (just) a show of words?"</rhetorical-question> Nay! to those who believe not, their pretence seems pleasing, but they are kept back (thereby) from the path. And those whom <repetition>Allah</repetition> leaves to stray, no one can guide. 
<milestone unit="verse" n="34" /><parallelism>For them is a penalty in the life of this world, but harder, truly, is the penalty of the Hereafter:</parallelism> and defender have they none against <repetition>Allah</repetition>. 
<milestone unit="verse" n="35" />The parable of the Garden which the righteous are promised!- beneath it flow rivers: perpetual is the enjoyment thereof and the shade therein: such is the end of the Righteous; and the end of Unbelievers in the Fire. 
<milestone unit="verse" n="36" />Those to whom We have given the Book rejoice at what hath been revealed unto thee: but there are among the clans those who reject a part thereof. Say: "I am commanded to worship <repetition>Allah</repetition>, and not to join partners with Him. <parallelism>Unto Him do I call, and unto Him is my return.</parallelism>" 
<milestone unit="verse" n="37" />Thus have We revealed it to be a judgment of authority in Arabic. <hyperbole>Wert thou to follow their (vain) desires after the knowledge which hath reached thee, then wouldst thou find neither protector nor defender against</hyperbole> <repetition>Allah</repetition>. 
<milestone unit="verse" n="38" />We did send messengers before thee, and appointed for them wives and children: and it was never the part of a messenger to bring a sign except as <repetition>Allah</repetition> permitted (or commanded). For each period is a Book (revealed). 
<milestone unit="verse" n="39" /><repetition>Allah</repetition> doth blot out or confirm what He pleaseth: with Him is the Mother of the Book. 
<milestone unit="verse" n="40" />Whether We shall show thee (within <repetiton>thy</repetiton> life-time) part of what we promised them or <personification>take to ourselves <repetition>thy</repetition> soul</personification> (before it is all accomplished),- <repetition>thy</repetition> duty is to make (the Message) reach them: it is our part to call them to account. 
<milestone unit="verse" n="41" />See they not that We gradually reduce the land (in their control) from its outlying borders? <parallelism>(Where) <repetition>Allah</repetition> commands, there is none to put back His Command:</parallelism> and He is swift in calling to account. 
<milestone unit="verse" n="42" />Those before them did (also) devise plots; but in all things the master-planning is <repetition>Allah</repetition>'s He <repetition>knoweth</repetition> the doings of every soul: and soon will the Unbelievers <repetition>know</repetition> who gets home in the end. 
<milestone unit="verse" n="43" />The Unbelievers say: "No messenger art thou." Say: "Enough for a witness between me and you is <repetition>Allah</repetition>, and such as have knowledge of the Book." 
</p></div1></body></text></TEI.2>