<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="MidTerm%20Schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<surah>
    <metadata>
        <title>Surah 13 The Thunder Ar-Rad</title>
        <editor>Muhammad Marmaduke Pickthall</editor>
        <translator>Muhammad Marmaduke Pickthall</translator>
        <source/>
    </metadata>
    <body>
        <ayah n="1"> Alif. Lam. Mim. Ra. These are verses of the Scripture. That which is revealed
            unto thee from thy Lord is the Truth, but most of mankind believe not. </ayah>
        <ayah n="2"> Allah it is Who raised up the heavens without visible supports, then mounted
            the Throne, and <device type="personification">compelled the sun and the moon to be of
                service, each runneth unto an appointed term </device>; He ordereth the
            course; He detaileth the revelations, that haply ye may be certain of the meeting with
            your Lord. </ayah>
        <ayah n="3"> And He it is Who spread out the earth and placed therein firm hills and flowing
            streams, and of all fruits He placed therein <device type="personification">two spouses (male and
                female)</device>. He covereth the night with the day. <device type="phatic">Lo!</device> herein verily are
            portents for people who take thought. </ayah>
        <ayah n="4"> And in the Earth are neighbouring tracts, vineyards and ploughed lands, and
            date-palms, like and unlike, which are watered with one water. And we have made some of
            them to excel others in fruit. <device type="phatic">Lo!</device> herein verily are portents for people who have sense. </ayah>
        <ayah n="5">
            <device type="repetition">And if thou wonderest, then wondrous is their saying</device>: <device type="rhetoricalQuestion">When we
            <device type="metaphor">are dust</device>, are we then forsooth (to be raised) in a new creation?</device> Such are they who
            disbelieve in their Lord; <device type ="imagery">such have carcans on their necks</device>; such are
            rightful owners of the Fire, they will abide therein. </ayah>
        <ayah n="6"> And they bid thee hasten on the evil rather than the good, when exemplary
            punishments have indeed occurred before them. But <device type="phatic">lo!</device> thy Lord is rich in pardon for
            mankind despite their wrong, and <device type="phatic">lo!</device> thy Lord is strong in punishment. </ayah>
        <ayah n="7"> Those who disbelieve say: If only some portent were sent down upon him from his
            <device type="phatic">Lord!</device> Thou art a warner only, and for every folk a guide. </ayah>
        <ayah n="8"> Allah knoweth that which every female beareth and that which the wombs absorb
            and that which they grow. And everything with Him is measured. </ayah>
        <ayah n="9"> He is the <device type="praise">Knower of the Invisible and the Visible</device>,<device type="praise"> the
                Great</device>, <device type="praise">the High Exalted</device>. </ayah>
        <ayah n="10">
            <device type="contrast">Alike of you is he who hideth the saying and he who noiseth it
                abroad</device>, <device type="contrast">he who lurketh in the night and he who goeth freely in
                the daytime.</device>
        </ayah>
        <ayah n="11"> For him are angels ranged before him and behind him, who guard him by Allah's
            command. <device type="phatic">Lo!</device> Allah changeth not the condition of a folk until they (first) change that
            which is in their hearts; and if Allah willeth misfortune for a folk there is none that
            can repel it, nor have they a defender beside Him. </ayah>
        <ayah n="12"> He it is Who showeth you the lightning, a fear and a hope, and raiseth the
            heavy clouds. </ayah>
        <ayah n="13"> The thunder hymneth His praise and (so do) the angels for awe of Him. He
            launcheth the thunderbolts and smiteth with them whom He will while they dispute (in
            doubt) concerning Allah, and He is mighty in wrath. </ayah>
        <ayah n="14"> Unto Him is the real prayer. Those unto whom they pray beside Allah respond to
            them not at all, <device type="imagery">save as (is the response to) one who stretcheth forth his
                hands toward water (asking) that it may come unto his mouth, and it will never reach
                it</device>. The prayer of disbelievers goeth (far) astray. </ayah>
        <ayah n="15"> And unto Allah falleth prostrate whosoever is in the heavens and the earth,
            willingly or unwillingly, as do their shadows in the morning and the evening hours. </ayah>
        <ayah n="16"> Say (O Muhammad): Who is <device type="praise">Lord of the heavens and the earth</device>?
            Say: Allah. Say: Take ye then (others) beside Him for protectors, which, even for
            themselves, have neither benefit nor hurt? Say: Is the blind man equal to the seer, or
            is darkness equal to light? Or assign they unto Allah partners who created the like of
            His creation so that the creation (which they made and His creation) seemed alike to
            them? Say: Allah is the <device type="praise">Creator of all things</device>, and He is <device type="praise">the
                One</device>, <device type="praise">the Almighty</device>. </ayah>
        <ayah n="17"> He sendeth down water from the sky, so that valleys flow according to their
            measure, and the flood beareth (on its surface) swelling foam - <device type="imagery">from that which
                they smelt in the fire in order to make ornaments and tools riseth a foam like unto
                it </device>- thus Allah coineth (the similitude of) the true and the false. Then,
            as for the foam, it passeth away as scum upon the banks, while, as for that which is of
            use to mankind, it remaineth in the earth. Thus Allah coineth the similitudes. </ayah>
        <ayah n="18"> For those who answered Allah's call is bliss; and for those who answered not
            His call, if they had all that is in the earth, and therewith the like thereof, they
            would proffer it as ransom. Such will have a woeful reckoning, and their habitation will
            be hell, a dire abode. </ayah>
        <ayah n="19"> Is he who knoweth that what is revealed unto thee from thy Lord is the truth
            like him who is blind? But only men of understanding heed; </ayah>
        <ayah n="20"> Such as keep the pact of Allah, and break not the covenant; </ayah>
        <ayah n="21"> Such as unite that which Allah hath commandeth should be joined, and fear
            their Lord, and dread a woeful reckoning; </ayah>
        <ayah n="22"> Such as persevere in seeking their Lord's Countenance and are regular in
            prayer and spend of that which We bestow upon them secretly and openly, and overcome
            evil with good. Theirs will be the sequel of the (heavenly) Home, </ayah>
        <ayah n="23"> Gardens of Eden which they enter, along with all who do right of their fathers
            and their helpmeets and their seed. The angels enter unto them from every gate, </ayah>
        <ayah n="24"> (Saying): Peace be unto you because ye persevered. Ah, passing sweet will be
            the sequel of the (heavenly) Home. </ayah>
        <ayah n="25"> And those who break the covenant of Allah after ratifying it, and sever that
            which Allah hath commanded should be joined, and make mischief in the earth: theirs is
            the curse and theirs the ill abode. </ayah>
        <ayah n="26"> Allah enlargeth livelihood for whom He will, and straiteneth (it for whom He
            will); and they rejoice in the life of the world, whereas <device type="contrast">the life of the
                world is but brief comfort as compared with the Hereafter</device>. </ayah>
        <ayah n="27"> Those who disbelieve say: If only a portent were sent down upon him from his
            <device type="phatic">Lord!</device> Say: <device type="phatic">Lo!</device> Allah sendeth whom He will astray, and guideth unto Himself all who turn
            (unto Him), </ayah>
        <ayah n="28"> Who have believed and whose hearts have rest in the remembrance of Allah.
            <device type="phatic">Verily in the remembrance of Allah do hearts find rest!</device> </ayah>
        <ayah n="29"> Those who believe and do right: Joy is for them, and bliss (their) journey's
            end. </ayah>
        <ayah n="30"> Thus We send thee (O Muhammad) unto a nation, before whom other nations have
            passed away, that thou mayst recite unto them that which We have inspired in thee, while
            they are disbelievers in the Beneficent. Say: He is my Lord; there is no Allah save Him.
            In Him do I put my trust and unto Him is my recourse. </ayah>
        <ayah n="31"> Had it been possible for a <device type="imagery">Lecture to cause the mountains to move, or
                the earth to be torn asunder, or the dead to speak,</device> (this Qur'an would
            have done so). Nay, but Allah's is the whole command. Do not those who believe know
            that, had Allah willed, He could have guided all mankind? As for those who disbelieve,
            disaster ceaseth not to strike them because of what they do, or it dwelleth near their
            home until the threat of Allah come to pass. <device type="phatic">Lo!</device> Allah faileth not to keep the tryst. </ayah>
        <ayah n="32"> And verily messengers (of Allah) were mocked before thee, but long I bore with
            those who disbelieved. At length I seized them, and <device type="phatic">how (awful) was My punishment!</device> </ayah>
        <ayah n="33"> Is He Who is aware of the deserts of every soul (as he who is aware of
            nothing)? Yet they ascribe unto Allah partners. Say: Name them. Is it that ye would
            inform Him of something which He knoweth not in the earth? Or is it but a way of
            speaking? Nay but their contrivance is made seeming fair for those who disbelieve and
            they are kept from the right road. He whom Allah sendeth astray, for him there is no
            guide. </ayah>
        <ayah n="34"> For them is torment in the life of the world, and verily the doom of the
            Hereafter is more painful, and they have no defender from Allah. </ayah>
        <ayah n="35"> A similitude of the Garden which is promised unto those who keep their duty
            (to Allah): <device type="contrast">Underneath it rivers flow; its food is everlasting, and its shade;
                this is the reward of those who keep their duty, while the reward of disbelievers is
                the Fire.</device>
        </ayah>
        <ayah n="36"> Those unto whom We gave the Scripture rejoice in that which is revealed unto
            thee. And of the clans there are who deny some of it. Say: I am commanded only that I
            serve Allah and ascribe unto Him no partner. Unto Him I cry, and unto Him is my return. </ayah>
        <ayah n="37"> Thus have We revealed it, a decisive utterance in Arabic; and if thou shouldst
            follow their desires after that which hath come unto thee of knowledge, then truly
            wouldst thou have from Allah no protecting friend nor defender. </ayah>
        <ayah n="38"> And verily We sent messengers (to mankind) before thee, and We appointed for
            them wives and offspring, and it was not (given) to any messenger that he should bring a
            portent save by Allah's leave. For everything there is a time prescribed. </ayah>
        <ayah n="39"> Allah effaceth what He will, and establisheth (what He will), and with Him is
            the source of ordinance. </ayah>
        <ayah n="40"> Whether We let thee see something of that which We have promised them, or make
            thee die (before its happening), thine is but conveyance (of the message). Ours the
            reckoning. </ayah>
        <ayah n="41"> See they not how we aim to the land, reducing it of its outlying parts? (When)
            Allah doometh there is none that can postpone His doom, and He is swift at reckoning. </ayah>
        <ayah n="42">
            <device type="contrast">Those who were before them plotted; but all plotting is Allah's</device>. He
            knoweth that which each soul earneth. The disbelievers will come to know for whom will
            be the sequel of the (heavenly) Home. </ayah>
        <ayah n="43"> They who disbelieve say: Thou art no messenger (of Allah). Say: Allah, and
            whosoever hath knowledge of the Scripture, is sufficient witness between me and you.
        </ayah>
    </body>
</surah>
