<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="englishschema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<surah>
    <metadata>
        <title>Surah 17 The Night Journey Al-Isrā</title>
        <editor/>
        <translator>Abdullah Yusuf Ali</translator>
        <source/>
    </metadata>
    <body>
        <ayah n="1">
            <device type="praise">Glory to (Allah)</device> Who did take His servant for a Journey
            by night from the Sacred Mosque to the farthest Mosque, whose precincts We did bless,-
            in order that We might show him some of Our Signs: for He is the One Who heareth and
            seeth (all things).</ayah>
        <ayah n="2">
            <device type="allusion">We gave Moses the Book, and made it a Guide to the Children of
                Israel, (commanding): "Take not other than Me as Disposer of (your)
                affairs."</device></ayah>
        <ayah n="3">
            <device type="allusion">O ye that are sprung from those whom We carried (in the Ark)
                with Noah! Verily he was a devotee most grateful.</device></ayah>
        <ayah n="4"> And We gave (Clear) Warning to the Children of Israel in the Book, that <device
                type="anaphora">twice would they</device> do mischief on the earth and be elated
            with mighty arrogance (and <device type="anaphora">twice would they</device> be
            punished)!</ayah>
        <ayah n="5"> When the first of the warnings came to pass, We sent against you Our servants
            given to terrible warfare: They entered the very inmost parts of your homes; and it was
            a warning (completely) fulfilled.</ayah>
        <ayah n="6"> Then did We grant you the Return as against them: <device type="parallelism">We
                gave you increase in resources and sons, and made you the more nerous in
                man-power.</device></ayah>
        <ayah n="7"> If <device type="anaphora">ye did</device> well, <device type="anaphora">ye
                did</device> well for yourselves; if <device type="anaphora">ye did</device> evil,
                (<device type="anaphora">ye did</device> it) against yourselves. So when the second
            of the warnings came to pass, (We permitted your enemies) <device type="metaphor">to
                disfigure your faces</device>, and to <device type="allusion">enter your Temple as
                they had entered it before</device>, and to visit with destruction all that fell
            into their power.</ayah>
        <ayah n="8"> It may be that your Lord may (yet) show Mercy unto you; <device
                type="parallelism">but if ye revert (to your sins), We shall revert (to Our
                punishments):</device> And <device type="irony">we have made Hell a prison</device>
            for those who reject (all Faith).</ayah>
        <ayah n="9"> Verily this Qur'an doth guide to that which is most right (or stable), and
            giveth the Glad Tidings to the Believers who work deeds of righteousness, that they
            shall have a magnificent reward;</ayah>
        <ayah n="10"> And to those who believe not in the Hereafter, (it announceth) that We have
            prepared for them a Penalty Grievous (indeed).</ayah>
        <ayah n="11">
            <device type="irony">The prayer that man should make for good, he maketh for
                evil;</device> for man is given to hasty (deeds).</ayah>
        <ayah n="12"> We have made the Night and the Day as two (of Our) Signs: <device
                type="parallelism">the Sign of the Night have We obscured, while the Sign of the Day
                We have made to enlighten you;</device>
            <device type="anaphora">that ye may</device> seek bounty from your Lord, and <device
                type="anaphora">that ye may</device> know the nber and count of the years: all
            things have We explained in detail.</ayah>
        <ayah n="13">
            <device type="metaphor">Every man's fate We have fastened on his own neck:</device> On
            the Day of Judgment We shall bring out for him a scroll, which he will see spread
            open.</ayah>
        <ayah n="14"> (It will be said to him:) "Read thine (own) record: Sufficient is thy soul
            this day to make out an account against thee."</ayah>
        <ayah n="15">
            <device type="parallelism">Who receiveth guidance, receiveth it for his own
                benefit</device>: who goeth astray doth so to his own loss: No bearer of burdens can
            bear the burden of another: nor would We visit with Our Wrath until We had sent an
            messenger (to give warning).</ayah>
        <ayah n="16"> When We decide to destroy a population, We (first) send a definite order to
            those among them who are given the good things of this life and yet transgress; so that
            the word is proved true against them: then (it is) We destroy them utterly.</ayah>
        <ayah n="17">
            <device type="rhetoricalQuestion">How many generations have We destroyed after
                Noah?</device> and enough is thy Lord to note and see the sins of His
            servants.</ayah>
        <ayah n="18">
            <device type="irony">If any do wish for the transitory things (of this life), We readily
                grant them - <device type="parallelism">such things as We will, to such person as We
                    will</device>: in the end have We provided Hell for them: they will burn
                therein, disgraced and rejected.</device></ayah>
        <ayah n="19"> Those who do wish for the (things of) the Hereafter, and strive therefor with
            all due striving, and have Faith,- they are the ones whose striving is acceptable (to
            Allah).</ayah>
        <ayah n="20"> Of the bounties of thy Lord We bestow freely on all- These as well as those:
            The bounties of thy Lord are not closed (to anyone).</ayah>
        <ayah n="21">
            <device type="contrast">See how We have bestowed more on some than on others</device>;
            but verily the Hereafter is more in rank and gradation and more in excellence.</ayah>
        <ayah n="22"> Take not with Allah another object of worship; or thou (O man!) wilt sit in
            disgrace and destitution.</ayah>
        <ayah n="23"> Thy Lord hath decreed that ye worship none but Him, and that ye be kind to
            parents. Whether one or both of them attain old age in thy life, <device
                type="parallelism">say not to them a word of contempt, nor repel them, but address
                them in terms of honour.</device></ayah>
        <ayah n="24"> And, out of kindness, <device type="metaphor">lower to them the wing of
                humility</device>, and say: "My Lord! bestow on them thy Mercy even as they
            cherished me in childhood."</ayah>
        <ayah n="25"> Your Lord knoweth best what is in your hearts: If ye do deeds of
            righteousness, verily He is Most Forgiving to those who turn to Him again and again (in
            true penitence).</ayah>
        <ayah n="26"> And render to the kindred their due rights, as (also) to those in want, and to
            the wayfarer: But squander not (your wealth) in the manner of a spendthrift.</ayah>
        <ayah n="27">
            <device type="parallelism">Verily spendthrifts are brothers of the Evil Ones; and the
                Evil One is to his Lord (himself) ungrateful.</device></ayah>
        <ayah n="28"> And even if thou hast to turn away from them in pursuit of the Mercy from thy
            Lord which thou dost expect, yet speak to them a word of easy kindness.</ayah>
        <ayah n="29">
            <device type="simile">Make not thy hand tied (like a niggard's) to thy neck, nor stretch
                it forth to its utmost reach, so that thou become blameworthy and
                destitute.</device></ayah>
        <ayah n="30"> Verily thy Lord doth provide sustenance in abundance for whom He pleaseth, and
            He provideth in a just measure. For He doth know and regard all His servants.</ayah>
        <ayah n="31"> Kill not your children for fear of want: We shall provide sustenance for them
            as well as for you. Verily the killing of them is a great sin.</ayah>
        <ayah n="32"> Nor come nigh to adultery: for it is a shameful (deed) and an evil, opening
            the road (to other evils).</ayah>
        <ayah n="33"> Nor take life - which Allah has made sacred - except for just cause. And if
            anyone is slain wrongfully, we have given his heir authority (to demand qisas or to
            forgive): but let him not exceed bounds in the matter of taking life; for he is helped
            (by the Law).</ayah>
        <ayah n="34"> Come not nigh to the orphan's property except to improve it, until he attains
            the age of full strength; and fulfil (every) engagement, for (every) engagement will be
            enquired into (on the Day of Reckoning).</ayah>
        <ayah n="35"> Give full measure when ye measure, and weigh with a balance that is straight:
            that is the most fitting and the most advantageous in the final determination.</ayah>
        <ayah n="36">
            <device type="imagery">And pursue not that of which thou hast no knowledge; for every
                act of hearing, or of seeing or of (feeling in) the heart will be enquired into (on
                the Day of Reckoning).</device></ayah>
        <ayah n="37"> Nor walk on the earth with insolence: for thou canst not rend the earth
            asunder, nor reach the mountains in height.</ayah>
        <ayah n="38"> Of all such things the evil is hateful in the sight of thy Lord.</ayah>
        <ayah n="39"> These are among the (precepts of) wisdom, which thy Lord has revealed to thee.
            Take not, with Allah, another object of worship, <device type="imagery">lest thou
                shouldst be thrown into Hell,</device> blameworthy and rejected.</ayah>
        <ayah n="40">
            <device type="rhetoricalQuestion">Has then your Lord (O Pagans!) preferred for you sons,
                and taken for Himself daughters among the angels?</device> Truly ye utter a most
            dreadful saying!</ayah>
        <ayah n="41">
            <device type="irony">We have explained (things) in various (ways) in this Qur'an, in
                order that they may receive admonition, but it only increases their flight (from the
                Truth)!</device></ayah>
        <ayah n="42"> Say: If there had been (other) gods with Him, as they say,- behold, they would
            certainly have sought out a way to the Lord of the Throne!</ayah>
        <ayah n="43">
            <device type="praise">Glory to Him! He is high above all that they say!- Exalted and
                Great (beyond measure)!</device></ayah>
        <ayah n="44">
            <device type="imagery">The seven heavens and the earth, and all beings therein, declare
                His glory:</device> there is not a thing but celebrates His praise; And yet ye
            understand not how they declare His glory! Verily He is Oft-Forbear, Most
            Forgiving!</ayah>
        <ayah n="45"><device type="imagery">When thou dost recite the Qur'an, We put, between thee
                and those who believe not in the Hereafter, a veil invisible:</device></ayah>
        <ayah n="46"> And We put coverings over their hearts (and minds) lest they should understand
            the Qur'an, and deafness into their ears: when thou dost commemorate thy Lord and Him
            alone in the Qur'an, <device type="imagery">they turn on their backs, fleeing (from the
                Truth).</device></ayah>
        <ayah n="47"> We know best why it is they listen, when they listen to thee; and when they
            meet in private conference, behold, the wicked say, "Ye follow none other than a man
            bewitched!"</ayah>
        <ayah n="48"> See what similes they strike for thee: but they have gone astray, and never
            can they find a way.</ayah>
        <ayah n="49"> They say: <device type="rhetoricalQuestion">What! when we are <device
                    type="metaphor">reduced to bones and dust,</device> should we really be raised
                up (to be) a new creation?"</device></ayah>
        <ayah n="50"> Say: "(Nay!) be ye stones or iron,</ayah>
        <ayah n="51"> "Or created matter which, in your minds, is hardest (to be raised up),- (Yet
            shall ye be raised up)!" then will they say: <device type="rhetoricalQuestion">"Who will
                cause us to return?"</device> Say: "He who created you first!" Then will they wag
            their heads towards thee, and say,<device type="rhetoricalQuestion">"When will that
                be?"</device> Say, "May be it will be quite soon!</ayah>
        <ayah n="52">
            <device type="imagery">It will be on a Day when He will call you, and ye will answer
                (His call) with (words of) His praise, and ye will think that ye tarried but a
                little while!"</device></ayah>
        <ayah n="53"> Say to My servants that they should (only) say those things that are best:
                <device type="anaphora">for Satan</device> doth sow dissensions among them: <device
                type="anaphora"><device type="allusion">For Satan</device> is to man an avowed
                enemy.</device></ayah>
        <ayah n="54"> It is your Lord that knoweth you best: <device type="contrast"><device
                    type="anaphora">If He please</device>, He granteth you mercy, or <device
                    type="anaphora">if He please</device>, punishment:</device> We have not sent
            thee to be a disposer of their affairs for them.</ayah>
        <ayah n="55"> And it is your Lord that knoweth best all beings that are in the heavens and
            on earth: We did bestow on some prophets more (and other) gifts than on others: <device
                type="allusion">and We gave to David (the gift of) the Psalms.</device></ayah>
        <ayah n="56"> Say: "Call on those - besides Him - whom ye fancy: they have neither the power
            to remove your troubles from you nor to change them."</ayah>
        <ayah n="57"> Those whom they call upon do desire (for themselves) means of access to their
            Lord, - even those who are nearest: <device type="contrast">they hope for His Mercy and
                fear His Wrath:</device> for the Wrath of thy Lord is something to take heed
            of.</ayah>
        <ayah n="58"> There is not a population but We shall destroy it before the Day of Judgment
            or punish it with a dreadful Penalty: that is written in the (eternal) Record.</ayah>
        <ayah n="59"> And We refrain from sending the signs, only because the men of former
            generations treated them as false: We sent the she-camel to the Thamud to open their
            eyes, but they treated her wrongfully: <device type="metaphor">We only send the Signs by
                way of terror</device> (and warning from evil).</ayah>
        <ayah n="60"> Behold! We told thee that thy Lord doth encompass mankind round about: We
            granted the vision which We showed thee, but as a trial for men,- as also the Cursed
            Tree (mentioned) in the Qur'an: We put terror (and warning) into them, but it only
            increases their inordinate transgression!</ayah>
        <ayah n="61">
            <device type="imagery">Behold! We said to the angels: "Bow down unto <device
                    type="allusion">Adam</device>": They bowed down except Iblis:</device> He said,
                <device type="rhetoricalQuestion">"Shall I bow down to one whom Thou didst create
                from clay?"</device></ayah>
        <ayah n="62"> He said: "Seest Thou? this is the one whom Thou hast honoured above me! If
            Thou wilt but respite me to the Day of Judgment, I will surely bring his descendants
            under my sway - all but a few!"</ayah>
        <ayah n="63"> (Allah) said: "Go thy way; if any of them follow thee, verily Hell will be the
            recompense of you (all)- an ample recompense.</ayah>
        <ayah n="64"> "Lead to destruction those whom thou canst among them, <device type="metaphor"
                >with thy (seductive) voice; make assaults on them with thy cavalry and thy
                infantry;</device> mutually share with them wealth and children; and make promises
            to them." But Satan promises them nothing but deceit.</ayah>
        <ayah n="65"> "As for My servants, no authority shalt thou have over them:" Enough is thy
            Lord for a Disposer of affairs.</ayah>
        <ayah n="66"> Your Lord is He That maketh the <device type="metaphor">Ship</device> go
            smoothly for you through the sea, in order that ye may seek of his Bounty. For he is
            unto you most Merciful.</ayah>
        <ayah n="67">
            <device type="irony">When distress seizes you at sea, those that ye call upon - besides
                Himself - leave you in the lurch! but when He brings you back safe to land, ye turn
                away (from Him).</device> Most ungrateful is man!</ayah>
        <ayah n="68">
            <device type="rhetoricalQuestion">Do ye then feel secure that He will not cause you to
                be swallowed up beneath the earth when ye are on land, or that He will not send
                against you a <device type="imagery">violent tornado (with showers of
                    stones)</device> so that ye shall find no one to carry out your affairs for
                you?</device></ayah>
        <ayah n="69">
            <device type="rhetoricalQuestion">Or do ye feel secure</device> that He will not send
            you back a second time to sea and send against you a heavy gale to drown you because of
            your ingratitude, so that ye find no helper. Therein against Us?</ayah>
        <ayah n="70"> We have honoured the sons of <device type="allusion">Adam</device>; provided
            them with transport on land and sea; given them for sustenance things good and pure; and
            conferred on them special favours, above a great part of our creation.</ayah>
        <ayah n="71"> One day We shall call together all human beings with their (respective) Imams:
            those who are given their record in their right hand will read it (with pleasure), and
            they will not be dealt with unjustly in the least.</ayah>
        <ayah n="72">
            <device type="parallelism">But those who were <device type="metaphor">blind</device> in
                this world, will be <device type="metaphor">blind</device> in the
                hereafter,</device> and most astray from the Path.</ayah>
        <ayah n="73"> And their purpose was to tempt thee away from that which We had revealed unto
            thee, to substitute in our name something quite different; (in that case), behold! they
            would certainly have made thee (their) friend!</ayah>
        <ayah n="74"> And had We not given thee strength, thou wouldst nearly have inclined to them
            a little.</ayah>
        <ayah n="75"> In that case We should have made thee taste <device type="anaphora">an equal
                portion</device> (of punishment) in this life, and <device type="anaphora">an equal
                portion</device> in death: and moreover thou wouldst have found none to help thee
            against Us!</ayah>
        <ayah n="76"> Their purpose was to scare thee off the land, in order to expel thee; but in
            that case they would not have stayed (therein) after thee, except for a little
            while.</ayah>
        <ayah n="77"> (This was Our) way with the messengers We sent before thee: thou wilt find no
            change in Our ways.</ayah>
        <ayah n="78"> Establish regular prayers - at the sun's decline till the darkness of the
            night, and the morning prayer and reading: for the prayer and reading in the morning
            carry their testimony.</ayah>
        <ayah n="79"> And pray in the small watches of the morning: (it would be) an additional
            prayer (or spiritual profit) for thee: soon will thy Lord raise thee to a Station of
            Praise and Glory!</ayah>
        <ayah n="80">
            <device type="parallelism">Say: "O my Lord! Let my entry be by the Gate of Truth and
                Honour, and likewise my exit by the Gate of Truth and Honour; and grant me from Thy
                Presence an authority to aid (me)."</device></ayah>
        <ayah n="81">
            <device type="contrast">And say: "Truth has (now) arrived, and Falsehood perished: for
                Falsehood is (by its nature) bound to perish."</device></ayah>
        <ayah n="82">
            <device type="contrast">We send down (stage by stage) in <device type="metaphor">the
                    Qur'an that which is a healing and a mercy to those who believe:</device> to the
                unjust it causes nothing but <device type="repetition">loss after
                loss</device>.</device></ayah>
        <ayah n="83">
            <device type="contrast">Yet when We bestow Our favours on man, he turns away and becomes
                remote on his side (instead of coming to Us)</device>, and when evil seizes him he
            gives himself up to despair!</ayah>
        <ayah n="84"> Say: "Everyone acts according to his own disposition: But your Lord knows best
            who it is that is best guided on the Way."</ayah>
        <ayah n="85"> They ask thee concerning the Spirit (of inspiration). Say: "The Spirit
            (cometh) by command of my Lord: of knowledge it is only a little that is communicated to
            you, (O men!)"</ayah>
        <ayah n="86"> If it were Our Will, We could take away that which We have sent thee by
            inspiration:then wouldst thou find none to plead thy affair in that matter as against
            Us,-</ayah>
        <ayah n="87"> Except for Mercy from thy Lord: for his bounty is to thee (indeed)
            great.</ayah>
        <ayah n="88"> Say: "If the whole of mankind and Jinns were to gather together to produce the
            like of this Qur'an, they could not produce the like thereof, even if they backed up
            each other with help and support.</ayah>
        <ayah n="89">
            <device type="irony">And We have explained to man, in this Qur'an, every kind of
                similitude: yet the greater part of men refuse (to receive it) except with
                ingratitude!</device></ayah>
        <ayah n="90"> They say: <device type="imagery">We shall not believe in thee, until thou
                cause a spring to gush forth for us from the earth,</device></ayah>
        <ayah n="91">
            <device type="imagery">Or (until) thou have a garden of date trees and vines, and cause
                rivers to gush forth in their midst, carrying abundant water;</device></ayah>
        <ayah n="92"> "Or thou cause the sky to fall in pieces, as thou sayest (will happen),
            against us; or thou bring Allah and the angels before (us) face to face:</ayah>
        <ayah n="93"> "Or thou have a house adorned with gold, or thou mount a ladder right into the
            skies. No, we shall not even believe in thy mounting until thou send down to us a book
            that we could read." Say: <device type="rhetoricalQuestion">"Glory to my Lord! Am I
                aught but a man,- a messenger?"</device></ayah>
        <ayah n="94"> What kept men back from belief when Guidance came to them, was nothing but
            this: they said, "Has Allah sent a man (like us) to be (His) Messenger?"</ayah>
        <ayah n="95"> Say, "If there were settled, on earth, angels walking about in peace and
            quiet, We should certainly have sent them down from the heavens an angel for a
            messenger."</ayah>
        <ayah n="96"> Say: "Enough is Allah for a witness between me and you: for He is well
            acquainted with His servants, and He sees (all things).</ayah>
        <ayah n="97"> It is he whom Allah guides, that is on true Guidance; but he whom He leaves
            astray - for such wilt thou find no protector besides Him. On the Day of Judgment
                <device type="imagery">We shall gather, them together, prone on their faces, blind,
                dumb, and deaf</device>: their abode will be Hell: every time it shows abatement, We
            shall increase from them the fierceness of the Fire.</ayah>
        <ayah n="98"> That is their recompense, because they rejected Our signs, and said, <device
                type="rhetoricalQuestion">When we are <device type="metaphor">reduced to bones and
                    broken dust</device>, should we really be raised up (to be) a new
                Creation?"</device></ayah>
        <ayah n="99">
            <device type="contrast">See they not that Allah, Who created the heavens and the earth,
                has power to create the like of them (anew)?</device> Only He has decreed a term
            appointed, of which there is no doubt. But the unjust refuse (to receive it) except with
            ingratitude.</ayah>
        <ayah n="100">
            <device type="irony">Say: "If ye had control of the Treasures of the Mercy of my Lord,
                behold, ye would keep them back, for fear of spending them: for man is (every)
                niggardly!"</device></ayah>
        <ayah n="101"> To Moses We did give Nine Clear Signs: As the Children of Israel: when he
            came to them, Pharaoh said to him: "O Moses! I consider thee, indeed, to have been
            worked upon by sorcery!</ayah>
        <ayah n="102"> Moses said, "Thou knowest well that these things have been sent down by none
            but the Lord of the heavens and the earth as eye-opening evidence: and I consider thee
            indeed, O Pharaoh, to be one doomed to destruction!"</ayah>
        <ayah n="103">
            <device type="irony"> So he resolved to remove them from the face of the earth: but We
                did drown him and all who were with him.</device></ayah>
        <ayah n="104"> And We said thereafter to the Children of Israel, "Dwell securely in the land
            (of promise)": but when the second of the warnings came to pass, We gathered you
            together in a mingled crowd.</ayah>
        <ayah n="105"> We sent down the (Qur'an) <device type="repetition">in Truth</device>, and
                <device type="repetition">in Truth</device> has it descended: and We sent thee but
                <device type="parallelism">to give Glad Tidings and to warn
            (sinners).</device></ayah>
        <ayah n="106">
            <device type="parallelism">(It is) a Qur'an which We have divided (into parts from time
                to time), in order that thou mightest recite it to men at intervals: We have
                revealed it by stages.</device></ayah>
        <ayah n="107"> Say: "Whether ye believe in it or not, it is true that those who were given
            knowledge beforehand, when it is recited to them, fall down on their faces in humble
            prostration,</ayah>
        <ayah n="108"> "And they say: 'Glory to our Lord! Truly has the promise of our Lord been
            fulfilled!'"</ayah>
        <ayah n="109"> They fall down on their faces in tears, and it increases their (earnest)
            humility.</ayah>
        <ayah n="110"> Say: "<device type="repetition">Call</device> upon Allah, or <device
                type="repetition">call</device> upon Rahman: by whatever name ye <device
                type="repetition">call</device> upon Him, (it is well): for to Him belong the Most
            Beautiful Names. Neither speak thy Prayer aloud, nor speak it in a low tone, but seek a
            middle course between."</ayah>
        <ayah n="111"> Say: <device type="praise">Praise be to Allah, who begets no son, and has no
                partner in (His) dominion: Nor (needs) He any to protect Him from humiliation: yea,
                magnify Him for His greatness and glory!"</device></ayah>
    </body>
</surah>
